<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>talk | Maurício Vancine</title>
    <link>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/category/talk/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://mauriciovancine.github.io/category/talk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>talk</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Maurício Vancine 2021</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2021 14:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>talk</title>
      <link>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/category/talk/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cartography Applications for Spatial Ecology</title>
      <link>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/talk/talk-sdm-uff/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2021 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/talk/talk-sdm-uff/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://mauriciovancine.github.io/talk/talk-sdm-uff/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Cartography has several applications in other areas of knowledge that need to perform the visualization of geospatial data. In this lecture I demonstrate some applications of cartography for Spatial Ecology, mainly in relation to Species Distribution Models.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Species Distribution Models: an overview</title>
      <link>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/talk/talk-sdm-gggc/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 09:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/talk/talk-sdm-gggc/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://mauriciovancine.github.io/talk/talk-sdm-gggc/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Species Distribution Models (SDMs) relate species occurrence data with their environmental conditions to estimate the species’ niche and thus predict new areas of possible distribution. In this lecture, I spoke of the main concepts, input data and applications of this approach in the area of Ecology.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ATLANTIC AMPHIBIANS: Atlantic Forest Amphibian Communities Dataset</title>
      <link>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/talk/talk-data-paper-amphibians-anfoco/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Aug 2018 16:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/talk/talk-data-paper-amphibians-anfoco/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://mauriciovancine.github.io/talk/talk-data-paper-amphibians-anfoco/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uncertainties about the diversity and distribution of species is one of the main challenges for conservation biology. The Atlantic Forest Biome is considered one of the most threatened biodiversity hotspots in the world, still holding a high number of amphibian species. In this work, we present a detailed compilation of amphibian communities for the Atlantic Forest. The data set was organized based on a wide geographical delimitation of the biome, encompassing ecotones and areas of Paraguay and Argentina. All community information was obtained from articles, books and unpublished literature (graduation monographs, dissertations and theses). We organize information about: 1) sampled habitat, 2) sampling methods, 3) sampling schedule, 4) sampling effort (initial and final month and year), 5) species composition or abundance, 6) endemism, and 7) location geographic (latitude, longitude, country, state, municipality and specific location). We made taxonomic updates based on data from the Amphibian Species of the World: an Online Reference database, for September 2017. The database was structured from 389 references, sampled between 1940 and 2017, which included 1,163 study, for which there are 17,619 records of 528 species with taxonomic certainty. Of the total records, 14,450 (82%) were classified according to the criterion of endemism to the Atlantic Forest Biome, of which 7,787 (44%) were considered endemic. The most representative methods were: 1) visual or auditory search (82.1%), 2) reproductive site search (20%), 3) trap and fall trap (pitfall, 15.3%), and 4) encounter occasional (14.5%). Among the sampled habitats, none was predominant, although the forest habitat was reported more frequently (40.7%). Most of the study sites had sampling carried out in bodies of water: stream within the forest (33.5%), permanent puddle (30.2%), lake (28.9%), marsh (28.6%) %), temporary pool (27.5%), semi-permanent pool (5.8%) and open water stream (4.5%). Species richness was 15.2 ± 11.3 SD, ranging from 1 to 80 species per location. There was a large sampling bias, with the majority of sampling carried out in the states of São Paulo (38.4%), Paraná (14.2%) and Minas Gerais (10.1%), collectively representing almost 63% of researches. This high bias for these three states may have been due to several reasons: 1) description of two or more study sites for the same reference; 2) historical process of training researchers, in addition to encouraging amphibian sampling research by the BIOTA-FAPESP Program; and 3) numerous herpetological collections, which possibly attracted researchers to carry out taxonomic works. The result of this data compilation generated an overview of the diversity, composition, methods and sampling effort of amphibian communities for the Atlantic Forest Biome, representing a huge effort to fill a knowledge gap about amphibian biodiversity in the Neotropical Region. We hope that these data can be used as a tool for the conservation of this group, in addition to being an important data source for studies of macroecological and biogeographic patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
